<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A second letter to a bishop from a minister of his diocess</title>
            <author>F. W., 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66232</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W25</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27048</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09626483</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09626483</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43854</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66232)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43854)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1345:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A second letter to a bishop from a minister of his diocess</title>
                  <author>F. W., 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Concerns schools, universities, clergy, and confirmation.</note>
                  <note>Signed: F.W.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England.</term>
               <term>Schools --  England.</term>
               <term>Confirmation --  Church of England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:43854:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43854:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Second Letter TO A BISHOP From A MINISTER OF HIS DIOCESS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year MDCXCII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:43854:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43854:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SInce my laſt of <hi>October</hi> 26, 1691, which you were pleaſed to thank me for, and to publiſh, I received your Lordſhip's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands by Mr. <hi>H.</hi> to add what hath ſince occurred to my Mind, concerning the ſame matter; and more particularly you require me to lay before you thoſe common Cauſes of the greateſt of our Evils, and the moſt powerful Remedies for the removing them. Since that time I have been hindred by a dangerous Sickneſs, the effects whereof I have not as yet got clear of: Beſides this, when I had recovered to ſome ſmall degree of Health, I met with other things which unavoida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly hindred me from obeying your Lordſhip's Commands. And having been thus long re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, I believe I had not entertained any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Thoughts of this matter, had I not by your Lordſhip's Letter, of <hi>Feb.</hi> 27. laſt paſt, been ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently urged to add what I had farther to ſay upon this occaſion.</p>
            <p>What I now trouble your Lordſhip with, is perfectly in obedience to your Commands, and the freedom I ſhall uſe proceeds from the ſame cauſe: For thô I have had ancient acquaintance
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:43854:3"/>with your Lordſhip in the Univerſity, yet that would not excuſe the Liberty I take, had I not been <hi>obliged</hi> by your <hi>Authority,</hi> as well as <hi>ſecured</hi> by your <hi>Friendſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a very unpleaſant thing to find fault, and eſpecially to me who know my own faults ſo well, that I cannot tell how to make ſevere Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections upon others. I am under no Diſcontent, I deſire no Preferment, am of no Party, and have no ill-will to any Man living: Beſides, I know 'tis very often an argument of a weak Mind, to cry out of the <hi>preſent</hi> time, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the <hi>paſt:</hi> And therefore I find my ſelf <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie</hi> under this <hi>Task.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But when I conſider to <hi>whom</hi> I write, and for <hi>what end,</hi> I cannot refuſe to ſay ſomething. For thô I take no pleaſure in ſeeing <hi>Wounds,</hi> and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king into <hi>Sores,</hi> yet I ſhould be too <hi>nice</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable</hi> alſo, ſhould I refuſe this where I had any proſpect of working a <hi>Cure.</hi> The Eyes of good Men are upon the Lords the Biſhops at this time, and 'tis greatly hoped you will be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairers of our Breaches; and you will greatly diſappoint the juſt expectations of the wiſe and good if ye be not. In view whereof I ſhall offer thoſe things which follow in this Paper. And I ſhall complain of no Evils but ſuch as the Biſhops, by their united Counſels and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:43854:3"/>by their Intereſt and their Influence, may in great meaſure remove. I ſay <hi>in great meaſure;</hi> for certain it is, that they cannot be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together removed. Some of them are ſuch, as when they are once admitted, they are not to be <hi>cured,</hi> but are like Errors in the <hi>firſt</hi> Concocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that are not to be amended <hi>afterwards.</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever this may be done; they may be for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture prevented, and the preſent Set of Biſhops may leave the Nation in a much better caſe than they found it. The Particulars which I humbly lay before your Lordſhip are theſe that follow.</p>
            <p n="1">I. The care of <hi>Schools.</hi> There are a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Number of theſe in your Lordſhip's Dioceſs, and ſome of them well endowed; your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip hath the Choice of one of the Maſters, and the Approbation of ſeveral; and none of them can Teach without a Licenſe from you. I hope many of the Maſters of theſe Schools diſcharge themſelves well; 'tis of great moment they ſhould all do ſo. I muſt needs ſay, I fear they do not. I once took an occaſion to ſpend ſome time in Examining one of them, at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of ſome Friends, whoſe Children were placed there for their better Inſtruction, and of one of the Governours of it. I was greatly ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized to find the Charity of the Pious Founder
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43854:4"/>abuſed, and the honeſt Deſign of the Parents of ſo many Children diſappointed. I'll tell your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip nothing but matter of Fact. In that great School there were not above two that underſtood any thing of their Grammar, even among thoſe who had been there above three Years. The firſt Rudiments were never taught them with care; and, for want of that, all the after-care imported nothing, and did but make the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren weary, and render the School a Priſon to them. I hoped, at leaſt, I ſhould have found them inſtructed in Religion, but they were ſo far from it, that they were not Taught any Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm at all by their Maſter, who never pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with them, nor took any care of their Souls. You cannot imagine what an Affliction this was to me. There muſt be ſome Remedy found out for this great Evil.</p>
            <p>Upon this Occaſion I humbly lay before you the following Particulars:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That there might be from time to time ſome certain and fixed times appointed for the ſtrict Examination of all publick Schools; This is practiſed with good ſucceſs in many great Schools, eſpecially about the City of <hi>London:</hi> If this were done with great care, and openly, you would ſoon find the good effects of it. I
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43854:4"/>could tell your Lordſhip where one of the beſt Schools in <hi>England</hi> had been utterly ruined, had it not been for this Care. The Governours of it, upon this publick Examination, removed the negligent Maſter, and placed another; who, by his great Care and Diligence, reſtored it from a very low Condition to a moſt flouriſhing one. 'Twill be no hard matter for your Lordſhip to accompliſh this. And you may find Men of Probity who will undertake this trouble, and give you a faithful account. But then they muſt enquire not only into the Learning, but Manners of the Scholars alſo; and what care hath been taken to bring them up <hi>in the nurture and admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of the Lord.</hi> I need not acquaint your Lordſhip how much the Publick is concerned in this matter. The timely Care of their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals may ſave many Souls, and prevent unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Miſchiefs which flow from want of an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and wiſe Diſcipline.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That for the future all poſſible Care be taken, that Men of great <hi>Probity</hi> be choſen Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Schools. Where the Biſhops nominate and approve, and, indeed, generally in all great Schools, this Care may be taken. The main Care is, that the Maſter of a School be a Perſon of great Probity, a Man of Vertue and Integrity,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43854:5"/>Yet Learning here is not to be deſpiſed, where it may be had, but not ſo much to be inſiſted on; For 'tis not neceſſary as Probity is. A little Learning with great Diligence, wiſe Diſcipline, good Temper, and hearty Love of God and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, is preferrable to the greateſt meaſure of Learning. I have known ſeveral Country School-Maſters, that had very little Learning them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that have had flouriſhing Schools, and ſome of the greateſt Men this Age hath known have been bred under them. But then they have been Men of great Wiſdom, and moſt exact Diſcipline; their Piety hath been great, and their Lives exemplary; and their Youth (like <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Lambs) have from what they ſaw in their Maſter's Lives, and from that goodly Idea of Religion which they laid before them, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived aright, and been formed into a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to the excellent Pattern laid in their way. I have the honour to know ſome Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Quality of ſingular Vertue, that do own the good which they received this way.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The Care of the <hi>Univerſities.</hi> This Care perhaps may not be thought to belong to the Biſhops, but to the Heads of Houſes, and Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows of Colleges. But ſtill it muſt be granted, that the united Endeavours of the Biſhops may
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43854:5"/>do much in this matter. For ſome of them are Heads of Colleges themſelves, others of them are Viſitors of them, and many of them have a great Influence upon thoſe Heads and Fellows as they are Deans or Dignitaries of their Churches, Chaplains in their Families, and have their Dependencies or Expectances from them. And very certain it is, that the want of good Diſcipline in the Univerſity is the Source of unſpeakable Miſchief to the whole Kingdom. For want of due Care in this Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Gentry have been corrupted, at leaſt not improved; The Country hath been filled with ignorant and indiſcreet Miniſters and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates; The People have taken occaſion to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake our Church; Schiſm hath been continued, and is like to be ſo; There are thoſe who durſt not truſt their Children there, and therefore have choſen to ſend them to St. <hi>Omers,</hi> or elſe have commended them to the Care of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters who have taught Schools, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken to Inſtruct them in the Univerſity Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; By this means they have been prejudiced againſt the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and many of them become the profeſſed Enemies of it. I am under no temptation to ſpeak hardly of our Univerſities, having had a Relation to both of them, and alſo being under great Obligations
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43854:6"/>to them. But yet I cannot but ſay that their Diſcipline of late Years hath been very lax; I have been ſometimes deſired to recommend a Number of young Gentlemen to the Care of Tutors, and have found it a very difficult Task to place them ſafely. 'Tis notorious, and not to be concealed; I have in paſſing through one of them, heard more Oaths ſworn by the Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, and more of them in or coming out of a Tavern, than I had obſerved whiles I lived there in many Years time. I make no doubt but ſome in each Univerſity have uſed great Care. But yet this could not avail much, when the greater Number were negligent; And ſome of the Governing part gave Example of great Intemperance by frequenting Taverns, or apoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing drinking Clubs in their Colleges. I know very well both the Men, and Places where they met, and did not only debauch themſelves but reproached better Men than themſelves over their Bottles, as Men not true to the Intereſt of their Church. The young Scholars were in the mean time neglected, permitted to frequent publick Houſes daily, and not called to a ſtrict account of their Studies or Manners. The Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes required by the Statute have been hud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled over, or bought off; Degrees given with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any merit; Preferments beſtowed by Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43854:6"/>and Letters of great Perſons; The Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Pious Benefactors perverted; Offices both publick and in <hi>particular</hi> Colleges not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, thô the Salary were received; Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments kept that were inconſiſtent with the Local Statutes; The Studious and Vertuous have been diſheartned; Eating and drinking to exceſs hath been the practice for many Years; I could ſay much more, and am very ſure I could prove it alſo. I had rather proceed to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer at ſome Remedy; I lay before your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the following Particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">(I.) That the firſt Care ſhould be to make the <hi>Univerſities</hi> Nurſeries of <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Vertue.</hi> The <hi>Learning</hi> which the young Student gets will do him or the World little good if his <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals</hi> be not ſecured: And indeed if his Vertue be preſerved, he is in a fairer way to get Learning alſo. This ought to be the firſt and greateſt Care; I wiſh it were not upon the matter wholly neglected. Your Lordſhip re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members the Words of <hi>Socrates</hi> before <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pias.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Xenoph. Mem. <hi>l. IV.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi> 'Tis</hi> (ſays he) <hi>a wonderful thing, that whereas if a man would put one out to learn a Trade or Art, he may eaſily find a Place where this may be learned; Nay more,</hi> 'tis ſaid, <hi>he may eaſily find thoſe who will teach an Ox or an Horſe to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43854:7"/>be tractable and uſeful. But if a Man were himſelf diſpoſed to learn what is Righteous, or would place out his Son or Servant to be taught it, he would not be able to find where to place himſelf or them.</hi> I believe there is nothing ſo hard and difficult a matter as to find a School of <hi>Vertue.</hi> We have often ſeen thoſe who went innocent to the Univerſities come thence depraved. And this hath many times happened through want of Care and diligent Application. That part of our Age which we ſpend there requires the utmoſt Care, and generally is neglected. There are very many that there have loſt their Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and Modeſty; That have been ſo far from Improvement there that they have been ruined. 'Twill ſtand you in hand to procure ſuch a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline, and order that it ſhall be an hard mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for a young Student to miſcarry. This will never be whiles they that are ſent thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for Inſtituton have the Liberty to live as they liſt. There muſt be great Care taken to form their Manners, to poſſeſs them with the Fear of God, and Senſe of a World to come; To convince them of the Difference of things; to principle them in true Religion, and every Vertuous thing. They muſt be kept from Wine and Wantonneſs; inured to Labour and Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe; reſtrained from the Converſation of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43854:7"/>Town; not ſuffered to go out of their Walls without leave; They muſt be ſtrictly kept to Prayers, and taught to pray by themſelves; inſtructed with exact Care for the Holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and kept to frequent Communion; the idle and vicious muſt be Carefully removed, and all ill Examples taken out of the way. The Heads and Governours of Colleges may with due Care turn their Colleges into Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Houſes; and 'tis hoped your Lordſhip and the other Biſhops will take this Matter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Conſideration, and do your utmoſt toward the effecting it.</p>
            <p n="2">(II.) 'Twill be highly fit that the <hi>Heads</hi> and other Governors ſhould be viſited. Indeed there are Viſitors appointed by the ſeveral Founders for ſome Colleges, and for ſome Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them in one of the Univerſities: But we have not ſeen any great Fruits of this Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. My meaning is, that ſome Number of Men ſhould be Commiſſioned from time to time to Viſit both Univerſities; Men that ſhould be Impowered to <hi>Examine</hi> ſtrictly into Things, and make Report, that the Negligent may be puniſhed ſeverely. I will not undertake to make Articles of Enquiry, but I think I may name ſome that will be needful, <hi>viz. How
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43854:8"/>the Eſtates of the Founder and Benefactors have been diſpenſed? How the Statutes of the Houſe have been obſerved? Have the Heads and Governors reſided as they ought? Have they kept no Place, nor been poſſeſt of Eſtates inconſiſtent with the Statutes of the Houſe? Have all Exerciſes been duly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed? Diligence and Vertue duly encouraged? What Lives do they lead? And what Account can they give of Themſelves and of their Time ſpent there? What Lectures are read by the Profeſſors and other Lecturers, and whether all be done which the Statute requires? Are thoſe Studies purſued Diligently which tend to make Men uſeful to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick? Are there no unſtatutable Fees exacted? No expenſive Cuſtoms introduced? No unneceſſary Eating-Houſes allowed?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Were theſe things looked into by Men of Authority, were the Criminals ſeverely puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſome of them that are moſt Guilty removed; were this done frequently, and with due Care, we ſhould ſoon ſee the good Effects of it. There would be another Face of things quickly; Prophaneneſs and Idleneſs would skulk preſently and ſoon be baniſhed; and Diligence and Vertue would revive and hold up their Heads. We have now many Men that have ſpent many Years there in order to ſerve the Church as they profeſs; when they come for
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43854:8"/>Orders they have not the Learning of ſome School-Boys. This I know upon my certain Knowledge, having been employed to Examine them when they offered themſelves to be Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained. I could give your Lordſhip a great many Inſtances of thoſe who have not had Skill enough to turn the Creed into true Latine, or an Article of Religion; And a great many others that had ſome of this Skill, yet had not any Underſtanding at all of <hi>Theological</hi> Matters; and yet were theſe Dunces admitted to Degrees, and brought Teſtimonials under the College Seal. My Lord, you cannot ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine with what Grief I write this: But thus it is; And there muſt be due Care taken of it.</p>
            <p n="3">(III.) Theſe <hi>Viſitors</hi> might be of farther Uſe if they had Orders to require ſome Publick Exerciſes whilſt they viſited; If they were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to bring with them a Liſt of the moſt Pious and Deſerving, that ſhould be kept in ſome publick Place; If they had Power to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point ſome Diſcipline, and revive the Exerciſes of greateſt Uſe that are now omitted. A great many things might be named under this Head which I forbear. One thing might eaſily be done, <hi>viz.</hi> The requiring all the Students to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43854:9"/>ſpeak the Latine Tongue within the Walls of their Houſe with each other. To do it at leaſt at their Meals. I remember well when this was done in a certain College, and with that ſucceſs that many of the Houſe had gained that readineſs, and were arrived to that Elegance that they far exceeded all Foreigners. 'Tis a ſhame Men ſhould be at a loſs in this Matter when every Foreigner hath attained it that knows any thing of Letters.</p>
            <p n="4">(IV.) 'Twill be neceſſary that greater Care be taken in beſtowing Degrees to thoſe only who deſerve them. That Teſtimonials be not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven promiſcuouſly; That the Good and Bad have not the ſame Teſtimony; That a Courſe and Method of Studies be contrived; That there be greater Care taken to encourage <hi>Mathematical</hi> Learning, and thoſe Parts of it eſpecially which are moſt for the Uſe of Life; That thoſe <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical</hi> Studies be commended which tend to make Men more Serviceable to the Church, and better able to Defend our Common Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity againſt all Gainſayers; That particular Care be taken to Direct young Students in their Study of the Scriptures.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:43854:9"/>
            <p n="3">III. There ought to be very great Care ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in admitting to <hi>Holy Orders.</hi> And this is a Care peculiarly belonging to the Biſhops. The want of this Care hath been attended with unſpeakable Miſchiefs. The Church groans under them, and is like to do ſo for ſome time. The Biſhops are the only Judges of the Fitneſs of Perſons that come to be Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, and may refuſe them that they judge unfit, without any danger of a <hi>quare im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedit,</hi> or any other Legal Moleſtation. But when they are admitted, a Biſhop runs an hazard, that refuſeth to give them Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. If another Biſhop Ordain an unfit Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and that Perſon be preſented to your Lordſhip to a Cure, you will find your ſelf under great Difficulty. If you admit him, you deliver up the Cure of Souls to a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon you do not Approve; If you refuſe him, you run the hazard of being ſued at Law. Indeed where you have Ordained a Perſon, you cannot reaſonably refuſe him Inſtitution when he deſires it. But 'tis very hard you ſhould be obliged to Inſtitute him whom another Biſhop hath without due Care ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Holy Orders. This careleſs ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43854:10"/>Men to Holy Orders, may, by the united Agreement of all the Biſhops, be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented for the future. I need not tell you what good Laws are made on this behalf, and how eaſie a thing 'twill be for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to take Care of this Matter. But eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Biſhop muſt take the utmoſt Care, and the Archbiſhops had need require a ſtrict and conſtant Account that others do their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. For if one Biſhop be Careleſs, as that Biſhop will be reſorted to and Ordain the greateſt Number, ſo the other Biſhops and the Church will ſuffer greatly by it. I know there have been ſome Biſhops that have been very remiſs; And ſome who have had a ſmall Dioceſs have had great Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and that when they lived remote from their Dioceſs alſo. This thing muſt be look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed after Diligently; and 'twere well that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Biſhop were obliged to give his Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litan an Account from time to time of the Number and Qualifications of all thoſe whom he admits into Holy Orders, and of the Places of their abode, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After all, the Biſhops had need be Care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful that they be not impoſed upon with falſe Titles, (a very common practice) with ſlight
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43854:10"/>Teſtimonials, and the perfunctory Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Chaplain. He had need Examine them himſelf, and require them that come for Orders to apply themſelves to him ſome conſiderable time before-hand, that he may be the better ſatisfied concerning them. Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wiſe Man will be very tender in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending a Perſon as a Servant to his Friend, much more if it be to a Place of any conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Truſt. What Care then ought the Biſhops to take when they Commend Men and Admit them to the Service of God, and of his Church, and the tremendous Care of Immortal Souls? The utmoſt Care in this Matter will be little enough. And were this Care taken by all the Biſhops; we ſhould ſoon ſee the bleſſed Fruits of it; young Men would ply their Studies, and take care of their Lives, and form themſelves to ſome ſhew at leaſt of Seriouſneſs in Religion. I know very well a certain excellent Prelate that hath in this Matter uſed Exemplary Care and Diligence; and I am told, by one that knows, the good Effects of it too. There are very few but have competently fitted themſelves before they have offered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to him: And for the Idle and Negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43854:11"/>that have heard of many ſuch refuſed, they have endeavoured with all their Skill to find means to be admitted into Holy Orders by ſome other hand. A due Care of this Matter would go a great way in that Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation which all good Men deſire, and juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hope from the preſent Biſhops. And this is no more than what is in your Power to do.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. A due Care of the <hi>Lives</hi> of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> and to ſee that they <hi>Reſide</hi> on their <hi>Cures</hi> and do their <hi>Duty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a great part of the Biſhops work. And they may do very much in it, and the Neceſſities of the Church and the Souls of Men call for it at your Hands. A wicked Clergy-Man does unſpeakable Miſchief. I know a conſiderable Town that was ſome Years ſince in good order, the People came conſtantly to Church, and they all did ſo: At the uſual times they came to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment alſo. But a lewd and ſcandalous Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter is now the Incumbent of that Place, one that is often diſordered with Drink, and ſwears commonly. The People are now diſperſed: They are run into ſeparate Meetings; and,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43854:11"/>in a word, the Town is ruined. I know the Truth of this; and can name ſeveral Places in your Lordſhip's Dioceſs where there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of this, thô I know no Place where it is ſo notorious as in that conſiderable Town. 'Twill be needful that ſome Remedy be found out for ſo great an Evil. I will not undertake to Direct your Lordſhip. 'Tis too evident how much the Church hath loſt by ſuch bad Men.</p>
            <p>Another Care is that of <hi>Reſidence,</hi> which is notoriouſly neglected. There are a great Number of Pariſhes that have no <hi>reſident Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter</hi> or <hi>Curate.</hi> Inſtead of that the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter comes or ſends every Sunday, and the Pariſhioners are deſtitute the reſt of the Week. There are many more Pariſhes which are great, and have a conſiderable Revenue, which are ſupplied by ſome cheap and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unfit Curates; By reaſon whereof the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are ſcattered, Parſonage-Houſes are dila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidated, Hoſpitality diſuſed; and, which is the ſaddeſt Conſideration of all, the Souls neglected. There are a Number of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in <hi>England</hi> that do not Reſide on their Livings: Some chuſe to live from their Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43854:12"/>in ſome great Towns at a diſtance for the ſake of Converſation, or Air, or upon ſome other Pretence: Some become Curates or Lecturers in other Places, and forſake their own Charge: Some are at the Univerſities on pretence of better fitting themſelves: Some lie about <hi>London,</hi> hunting after another Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, or ſome Lecture there. Some are in the Families of Perſons of Honour, others hang about the Court; and ſome are in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral-Churches in ſome Employment there, and notoriouſly neglect their cure of Souls in the mean time. I know ſome that are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Strangers to their People that ſee them not in ſeveral Years, and upon the matter never preach with them. I know a Perſon that hath one of the beſt Livings in <hi>England,</hi> and hath had for ſixteen Years laſt paſt, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver preached among them; not for want of Ability, or Leiſure, or becauſe he hath any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Cure, or Publick Employment, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is not reconciled to the Labour of his Calling. I could enlarge very much on this Head, and yet not borrow Materials from others. I have ſeen and do very well know many of the Neglects of this kind. I am amazed when I ſeriouſly conſider it, and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43854:12"/>how theſe Men can look up to Heaven, or with what Brow they can look honeſt Men in the Face when they are conſcious of ſo great a Sin? 'Tis time for the Biſhops to look after this Matter, as they would not have the Blood of the neglected Souls lie up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them.</p>
            <p>But your Lordſhip will ſay, How can this be prevented? For a great Number of theſe Perſons have Qualifications and Diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſome others are abſent for Health, or Studies, and other reaſonable Cauſes.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, That this will not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe them that have no reaſonable Cauſe for their Abſence, nor any longer than that Cauſe continues. I know ſeveral Men that live at the Univerſities to a conſiderable Age, and are never like to be more fit than they are. Theſe Men ought to go to their Cures, and ſo ſhould thoſe Men too, who withdrew for want of Health when their Health is reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. The <hi>Diſpenſations</hi> to hold two Livings will not excuſe a Man from not reſiding upon either. And that hath too often been the Caſe. Beſides, 'tis very fit thoſe Diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43854:13"/>ſhould be very rarely given, and 'tis in the Power of the Archbiſhop to reſtrain them. 'Tis no creditable thing for a Man to need a Diſpenſation generally ſpeaking; And thô where one Living is not a Maintenance, and another ſmall one is near it, a Diſpenſation to hold thoſe two may be a very allowable thing, yet this will not excuſe the promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous allowance of Diſpenſations. I know a great Number of Men that have Plurality of the beſt Livings, and thoſe too at a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable diſtance; and the ſame Men that have two great Livings apiece, have many of them beſides <hi>one,</hi> ſome <hi>two</hi> or <hi>three</hi> Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties apiece. Great have been the Miſchiefs of <hi>Non Obſtante</hi>'s and <hi>Diſpenſations.</hi> They were firſt uſed in the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Godol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin. Reper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nic. <hi>p. 300.</hi>
               </note> 'Twas an ill Preſident and Miſchievous to all the Commonwealths of Chriſtendom. For the Temporal Princes perceiving that the Pope diſpenſed with Canons, in imitation thereof have uſed their Prerogative to Diſpenſe with their Penal Laws and Statutes, when as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they cauſed their Laws to be Religiouſly obſerved, like the Laws of <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> which cannot be diſpenſed with. For this reaſon it was that a <hi>Canoniſt</hi> ſaid, <hi>Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatio
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:43854:13"/>eſt vulnus quod vulnerat jus commune.</hi> Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaith, That all Abuſes of this kind would be reformed, <hi>Si duo tantùm verba [non Obſtante] non Impedirent.</hi> And <hi>Matth. Paris,</hi> having recited certain Decrees made in the Council of <hi>Lyons,</hi> which were beneficial for the Church of <hi>England,</hi> addeth, <hi>Sed haec om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia &amp; alia per hoc repagulum [non Obſtante] in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmantur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After all 'tis certain, that there are very many <hi>Non-reſidents</hi> who have no Diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor Excuſe that is reaſonable. 'Tis pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty but theſe ſhould be obliged to reſide, or proceeded againſt according to the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes in that behalf. If they were duly pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, according to Law, we ſhould ſoon find the good Effects of it.</p>
            <p>I have heard ſome wiſe Men affirm, who underſtand the preſent Poſture of things in the City of <hi>London,</hi> that there are a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Number of Men there, who are Curates, or Lecturers, or Readers, or at leaſt Candidates for ſuch Places, that have Cures in the Country which they leave, and ſome of thoſe Cures not well provided for. If
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43854:14"/>this be ſo, I am ſure 'tis a great Evil: But this is an Evil eaſily cured. The Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> may put a ſtop to it when he pleaſeth. And I believe he will do it; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I know he is a Prelate of great Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, of moſt Exemplary Diligence and Care; and of ſo great Wiſdom beſides, that he cannot but diſcern the Miſchievous Effects of ſuch a Permiſſion. Were he put in Mind of this Matter, certainly he would never Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe any Curate or Lecturer there who had a Cure elſewhere. And did he once take up this Reſolution, he would ſoon diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage this ſort of Men. 'Tis of vaſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence that the City of <hi>London</hi> ſhould be well ſupplied: And that it may be, without employing Men that have Cure of Souls al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready. And this I muſt needs ſay, That thô I have ſometimes heard that there are ſuch Men employed in the City, I cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve they are Approved or Licenſed by that Eminent Biſhop.</p>
            <p>But your Lordſhip is not only to take Care that your Clergy <hi>Reſide,</hi> but that they do their <hi>Duty</hi> alſo: And that amounts to a great deal more than <hi>Preaching</hi> every <hi>Sunday,</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:43854:14"/>and Reading Prayers on <hi>Wedneſdays, Fridays,</hi> and <hi>Holy-days.</hi> Sick People are to be viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the Poor to be provided for, young Ones to be inſtructed, the Good to be encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, the Afflicted to be comforted, the Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minals to be admoniſhed, the Contentious to be reconciled.</p>
            <p>There are many Emergencies to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for. The Miniſter is the common Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his People. He is always wanted, and the utmoſt Care he can take, the moſt Time he can ſpare will be all little enough to ſpend among them. The very Catechizing the Youth of his Pariſh, preparing them for Confirmation firſt, and then for the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lord's-Supper will require great Thought and Pains. The bare ſaying the Catechiſm is not enough. They muſt be brought to Underſtand their Religion, and made ſenſible how much 'tis their Intereſt and their Duty. The leaſt Pariſh will need the Preſence and Labour of its Paſtor. This is not to be left to a raw Curate. We af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front Almighty God by taking this Courſe, and do in this greateſt Concern what is never allowed in things of leſs Moment.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:43854:15"/>When we have retained a learned Phyſician, or Lawyer, we will not give them the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to ſubſtitute and put upon us ſome unskilful Apothecary, or young Attorney. Our Concerns are of greater Value than to be thus left. And ſure our Souls are of greater Worth than our Lives or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates.</p>
            <p n="5">V. A greater Care concerning <hi>Confirmation</hi> of thoſe who have not been confirmed before. The Truth of it is, that this hath been often <hi>huddled</hi> over, and with little Fruit. Whereas it is not only an excellent Inſtitution of it ſelf, but may be ſo managed alſo as to be of unſpeakable Uſe. Thoſe that are to be Confirmed had need be prepared for it, and the Thing ought to be done with great So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity. To that purpoſe I humbly offer the following Particulars to your Lordſhip's Conſideration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That there ſhould be Notice given of a Confirmation ſome conſiderable time before, and that the Miniſter be required to Prepare the Youth of his Pariſh for it; That he have Notice to Inſtruct them
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43854:15"/>with great Care, not only in the bare get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Catechiſm by Heart, but in ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling them to give ſuch an Account of the Meaning of what they ſay, and ſo poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them with the Obligation lying upon them from their Baptiſmal Vow, that they may be fitly diſpoſed to receive great Benefit thereby.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That none be offered to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop but ſuch as the Miniſter of the Pariſh hath thus prepared. And to this purpoſe the Miniſter may be obliged to deliver to the Biſhop a Liſt or Catalogue of thoſe who are to be Confirmed by him, together with a Certificate under his Hand and Seal at the bottom of it; in which he ſhall Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie that he hath Examined and does Approve of the Perſons above-named in Number........ and judgeth them fit to be Confirmed. It is to be ſuppoſed no Miniſter will give this Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificate without good Cauſe. However the Biſhop may upon occaſion ſo order the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that he may have ſome of them for tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Examined before they are Confirmed, that he may find out the Fraud if he think it fit, and have any cauſe to fear due Care hath
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:43854:16"/>not been taken. By this courſe they who are to be Confirmed may be called by Name, and the Biſhop will not be crowded by thoſe who are not Inſtructed, and by thoſe who have been Confirmed before. For it hath been obſerved, that many will be Confirmed often, and many others before they are In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, and others that are ſo young that they cannot underſtand what they do.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> 'Tis very fit there ſhould be a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon preached on this Solemn Occaſion, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth the Grounds upon which Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation is Built, the Advantages of it, with a particular Addreſs to thoſe who are to be Confirmed; or elſe the Preacher may diſcourſe of the Baptiſmal Vow, and of the Reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs of taking that Obligation upon our ſelves, which was promiſed in our Infancy by our Sureties: But your Lordſhip may chuſe a wiſe and good Man for this Service, and then he will be at no loſs for his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Your Lordſhip may conſider alſo, whether it might not be fit ſome little Book ſhould be deviſed by common Conſent of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:43854:16"/>the Biſhops, which might be of after-uſe to them who are Confirmed; which Book may be delivered to each of them at the time of their Confirmation, <hi>gratis,</hi> (by the Biſhop's own Hand) with an Obligation laid upon them to read it. In this Book there ought to be ſome Prayers, and Inſtructions towards the Preparing for the Holy Sacrament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> The ſeveral Miniſters are to be ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charged to have a watchful Eye over thoſe who are thus Confirmed, and to Prepare them for the Sacrament of the Lord's-Supper as ſoon after as is fit and convenient.</p>
            <p>Theſe are my ſudden Thoughts of this Matter. Your Lordſhip is the beſt Judge of the whole. Thus much is certain, that if this Care were taken, or ſome better, thoſe who now deſpiſe it would be very glad of this bleſſed Opportunity of engaging Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, their Children, and their Servants, to the Obedience of Chriſt and his Holy Laws. This Service might be ſo managed that it would be of great Uſe to the Souls of Men.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:43854:17"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> There ought to be the utmoſt <hi>Care</hi> taken of Market-Towns that they be well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided (if poſſible) with able Miniſters, and Men of a good Life, and Men that ſhall preach twice a-day alſo. For if they be well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, the little Pariſhes about them will be the better for it. For as good Preaching in <hi>London</hi> (a Place of great Reſort from all Parts of the Kingdom) hath a mighty Influence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the whole Nation, ſo in proportion it muſt be in all Market-Towns, to which the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try People come, and the Miniſters of the Villages alſo. A wiſe Man there is conſulted upon Occaſion by the other Clergy-Men; and a great Example of Vertue in an Eminent Place goes farther than the ſame in a Village, or little Hamlet. I confeſs the Maintenance here is generally ſmall, but then they ought to be encouraged by what other Helps the Biſhops can afford them; And ſome of the Biſhops have Prebends and other ſmall Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities to beſtow, which cannot be better pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced than upon the worthy Miniſters of ſuch Places; who as they have the greater Charge and Work, ſo ought to have the greater En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement. Beſides, theſe are the Places
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:43854:17"/>where the Diſſenters, that preach, generally are; And indeed here are the greateſt Number generally of that ſort of People. I have known ſeveral of theſe Places preſerved from Schiſm and Faction by watchful, and diligent, and prudent Paſtors; and (I ſpeak it with grief) a great many of them miſerably divided from our Church through the Negligence, and Folly, and Wickedneſs of their Miniſters: Some of which have refuſed to Preach in an Afternoon, when it hath been much deſired; others have ſpent their Pains in the Pulpit generally in bitter Invectives againſt the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters; others have gone beyond the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick, and refuſed to pleaſe their People where they might have done it without breaking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Law; ſome have ſided with Parties, and inſtead of ending Differences have been of a certain Party in them; and others have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with their Neighbours for Trifles, fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into Heats with them, and then have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to Viſit them or do them Civil Offices. The Diſſenters have taken Occaſion to ſet up Preaching in their Towns and drawn away their People. The Schiſm hath hereby grown great, and the Miniſter himſelf hath had too
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:43854:18"/>much hand in it, notwithſtanding his warm Declamations againſt it. My Heart akes when I ſeriouſly think of this. And 'twill be worth the utmoſt Care of all the Biſhops how to get this Evil at leaſt leſſened, if not quite re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved. The Care of theſe great Places con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the whole, and 'twill become the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops to find ſome way by themſelves, or their Intereſt at Court, or elſewhere, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure ſome additional Maintenance for thoſe who are Diligent and Painful in theſe Places. Great Cities and Towns (and the Univerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties eſpecially) moſt need warm and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Preachers, and 'twill be great Charity to provide them with ſuch. And thus, my Lord, I have ſpoken my Mind frankly. Some per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps will think I have uſed too great Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: Nor ſhall I wonder at it: For perhaps I have not conſidered you in this Letter as my Dioceſan, but have uſed that Freedom which I was wont to uſe with you when I knew you in the Univerſity. If I have done ſo, 'tis not for want of Deference for your Perſon and your Character.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:43854:18"/>
            <p>I make no queſtion but when you come among us, and in your Viſitation, you will anſwer the expectations of your Friends, and at leaſt ſilence your Enemies. I doubt not but you will do all you can (and you may do much by your Example and Authority) to make us better, and to work a Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which all good Men expect and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire. You will find many of your Clergy very complying in thoſe excellent Deſigns. If you mind them of their Duty (as I am ſure you will) I dare aſſure you of a great Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ready to aſſiſt you.</p>
            <p>'Tis high time to be doing that great Work which you intend. There are a conſiderable Number that expect your Commands, and greatly hope you will vigorouſly Encourage us to look after our Cures, to Inſtruct our Youth, to ſet up Prayers in all the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies of our Pariſhioners, and to preach up the Neceſſity of Reformation, and preach againſt the Vices that reign amongſt us, and to do it with great Care and Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:43854:19"/>
            <p>I am very certain (as bad as the World is) that by this Method you will be an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of much Good to the Souls of Men. That you may be ſo, is the moſt ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord</salute>,
<signed>Your Lordſhip's Moſt Obedient Servant, <hi>F. W.</hi>
               </signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>March</hi> 26. 1692.</date>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:43854:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
